<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>System Administration on Quakkels.com</title>
    <link>https://quakkels.com/tags/system-administration/</link>
    <description>Recent content in System Administration on Quakkels.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://quakkels.com/tags/system-administration/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>GitHub Pages and Quakkels.com</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/quakkels-dot-com-now-with-https/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/quakkels-dot-com-now-with-https/</guid>
      <description>So I must&amp;rsquo;ve been under a rock for the last 21 months because it wasn&amp;rsquo;t until this week that I learned that GitHub Pages now supports SSL certificates for custom domains. They&amp;rsquo;ve had SSL support since 2016 for sites using {user}.github.io domains. But it has also been available for custom domain sites (like this one) since May of 2018.
Before the feature was upgraded there were hacks to get around the custom domain limitation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Run Plex on an Ubuntu Server at Home</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/run-plex-on-ubuntu-server-at-home/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/run-plex-on-ubuntu-server-at-home/</guid>
      <description>Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve decided that having limited high quality entertainment choices is better than having endless choices that are of questionable quality. So my household decided to end our Netflix subscription. This decision motivated me to build a private streaming media server for our home. Here is how I created a home media server with Plex and a home server tower.
Choosing the Media Server There are two popular software options for home media server.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Configuring Vim When Using Git Bash on Windows</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/configuring-vim-when-using-git-bash/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/configuring-vim-when-using-git-bash/</guid>
      <description>Occasionally I become enamored with the idea of becoming a Vim expert, or at least a competent Vim user. I work primarily in Windows environments so, though the desire exists, there aren&amp;rsquo;t many good opportunities to build Vim habits. There is a Vim on Windows release available. This has a GUI interface and an installer executable. Though if you have Git for Windows installed, then you already have Vim available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL Quick Reference</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/mysql-quick-reference/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/mysql-quick-reference/</guid>
      <description>Shell Commands Set up security requirements: $ sudo mysql_secure_installation  Open the MySQL CLI client and login using a password and the specified user: $ sudo mysql -u {user} -p  MySQL Queries and Commands  Note that MySQL will not execute anything until it encounters a semicolon ; which indicates the end of a statement. This allows us to enter multi-line statements.
 Create User &amp;gt; CREATE USER &#39;newuser&#39;@&#39;localhost&#39; IDENTIFIED BY &#39;password&#39;;  Give User Access to a Database &amp;gt; GRANT ALL PRIVILEGES ON * .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gogs on Raspberry PI</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/gogs-on-raspberry-pi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/gogs-on-raspberry-pi/</guid>
      <description>In a previous article I configured a headless Raspberry Pi for Wifi and SSH. Next, I&amp;rsquo;ll set up a personal Gogs server on it.
Change the Password First things first, change the password for the pi user to something different than raspberry.
$ passwd Changing password for pi. (current) UNIX password: Enter new UNIX password: Retype new UNIX password: passwd: password updated successfully  Please tweet your new password to @quakkels /s</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Configure Headless Raspberry Pi for Wifi and SSH</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/configure-headless-raspberry-pi-for-wifi-and-ssh/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/configure-headless-raspberry-pi-for-wifi-and-ssh/</guid>
      <description>Raspberry Pis are great little computers. Wonderful for running hobby services. But, whenever I start a new RPi project, I dislike needing to dig out my spare HDMI monitor and USB keyboard. I don&amp;rsquo;t like having to take up room and connect all that hardware to just enable SSH and Wifi which renders all that equipment unnecessary.
Recently I learned how to flash a new micro SD card and configure it to connect to my Wifi network and enable SSH before even turning on the RPi for the first time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Into the Nether: Linux</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/into-the-nether-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/into-the-nether-linux/</guid>
      <description>The first movie I saw that really got me excited about computers was WarGames. The WOPR was an inanimate object that just sat there on screen. But, it was still a complete character all by itself. It reacted to the Matthew Broderick character&amp;rsquo;s commands and questions and became something more clever than just a boring piece of hardware. The fictional software running inside the WOPR and Broderick&amp;rsquo;s character&amp;rsquo;s ability to interface with it created a story that was incredibly mystical and exciting.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>