<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tips on Quakkels.com</title>
    <link>http://quakkels.com/tags/tips/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tips on Quakkels.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://quakkels.com/tags/tips/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>5 Slack Tricks that Changed My Life</title>
      <link>http://quakkels.com/posts/5-slack-tricks-that-changed-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://quakkels.com/posts/5-slack-tricks-that-changed-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://quakkels.com/images/clickbait.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Please excuse the &amp;ldquo;click-baity&amp;rdquo; title. Sometimes I like to exaggerate.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slack plays a significant role in my daily communication. My team at work has been using Slack as our primary mode of textual communication for over a year. It is also used by developer communities in my local area. At first, it felt a little clumsy. No more clumsy than a typical chat program. But, channels started to accumulate. The number of Direct Message feeds grew. Navigating and filtering all the conversations became more cumbersome. The tricks I will discuss here have helped me to stay nimble in Slack&amp;rsquo;s user interface. At first, I looked at Slack as a swamp of messages that I needed to wade through. But, with these small tricks, Slack has become easier to use and it even plays more of a productivity role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ctrl+k&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are in a large Slack room with many channels, &lt;code&gt;ctrl+k&lt;/code&gt; can be a lifesaver! It gives you quick access to a list of channels that have new conversations. It also has an easy to use search feature that allows the user to navigate from their current conversation to a different channel or user. For someone like me, this is life changing. I love being able to use as much software as I can without needing to use my mouse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;/remind&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, I thought the &lt;code&gt;/remind&lt;/code&gt; feature was a gimmick that wasn&amp;rsquo;t useful. So it took me a few months to even try it out for the first time. Once I tried it, I became dependent on it. Some of the ways to use this include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remind yourself to follow up with a colleague the next day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remind yourself to start or end work on a project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right before leaving work, you can remind yourself to run an errand on the way home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite way to use &lt;code&gt;/remind&lt;/code&gt; is to set time-limits on periods of
concentration. Outlook does a similar thing for meetings. About 15 minutes
ahead of time, Outlook can pop up reminders that a meeting is approaching.
I like to use &lt;code&gt;/remind&lt;/code&gt; in a similar way for things that aren&amp;rsquo;t on my calendar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I may need to switch concentration contexts midway through the
day. I can use &lt;code&gt;/remind me to work on XyzProject in 2 hours&lt;/code&gt;. Once the
reminder has been set, it&amp;rsquo;s easier for me to concentrate on the current
task because I don&amp;rsquo;t need to keep project &amp;lsquo;XyzProject&amp;rsquo; in the back of my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;/remind&lt;/code&gt; is also useful for helping me remember the state a project was in
when I left it. For example, I can say &lt;code&gt;/remind me to bind new service 
implementations with Ninject on Monday at 8am&lt;/code&gt;. This has been a great tool
to get me working on a project right where I left off.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Star important channels&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a cool little trick the helps me group my highest priority channels together. At work, I have a handful of channels that are team specific. I like to star those so they all get prioritized at the top of the list. Then all the other channels, which are company-wide, get grouped below the starred channels. It&amp;rsquo;s the simplest thing, but works so well. Just select the channel and hover over the channel&amp;rsquo;s name at the top. Then a click-able star button will appear.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;/mute&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;/mute&lt;/code&gt; has been useful for me at work where I&amp;rsquo;m in many channels. However, I don&amp;rsquo;t need constant notifications whenever someone has added a post. &lt;code&gt;/mute&lt;/code&gt; has been a great tool for alleviating the tsunami of push notifications that I would have otherwise received.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;/collapse&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If people are going nuts with &lt;code&gt;/giphy&lt;/code&gt; or posting URLs that automatically show previews, then use &lt;code&gt;/collapse&lt;/code&gt; to clean up that clutter in one giant swoop!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So those are my 5 Slack tips. But wait! There&amp;rsquo;s more. So here are a few bonus tips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;up-arrow&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know I&amp;rsquo;ve made posts that have errors in them. You can use the up arrow key to edit your last post, or even delete it entirely. If editing, I recommend surrounding the part that was wrong with &lt;code&gt;~&lt;/code&gt; and then adding your new edit after that. This is good helps people see what has changed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ctrl+/&lt;/code&gt; brings up a help menu.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>