<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Fitness on Quakkels.com</title>
    <link>http://quakkels.com/tags/fitness/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Fitness on Quakkels.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://quakkels.com/tags/fitness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Home Gym Outfitting; Train with a Sled</title>
      <link>http://quakkels.com/posts/home_gym_outfitting_train_with_a_sled/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://quakkels.com/posts/home_gym_outfitting_train_with_a_sled/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Outfitting a home gym with a sled for drags and arm-over-arm pulls is simple. You don&amp;rsquo;t need to spend hundreds of dollars on equipment or gym memberships in order to train with a sled. You also don&amp;rsquo;t really need any tools or handyman skills to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first wanted to add arm-over-arm pulls to work my cardio, grip, arms, and back, I looked around and found a &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;https://www.roguefitness.com/conditioning/strength-equipment/sleds&#34;&gt;few different options&lt;/a&gt;. And some of them were rather economical. However, most are still priced near a hundred dollars and they don&amp;rsquo;t include a rope nor a strap long enough for arm-over-arm pulls, which I&amp;rsquo;d have to purchase separately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a simpler and cheaper alternative to those econo sleds. It can be found at the local hardware store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tow strap cost me just about ten dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://quakkels.com/images/new_tow_strap.png&#34; alt=&#34;20&#39; Tow Strap&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I combine it with a few of my bumper plates, it does exactly what I need. Ta-da! A &amp;ldquo;sled&amp;rdquo; for my home gym.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://quakkels.com/images/first_sled_experiment.png&#34; alt=&#34;Arm-over-arm pull with a 20&#39; tow strap&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This first experiment was awesome. It was easy to set up and it worked. Though, I did I noticed wear on the strap underneath the bumper plates. At first I thought it was no big deal. But if I had to replace the fraying strap a few times my costs would eventually be comparable with if I had bought an actual post style sled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to address the wear on the strap, I made a sheath using a an easily replaceable resource I frequently have lying around; a piece of cardboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://quakkels.com/images/sled_experiment_with_cardboard_sheeth.png&#34; alt=&#34;A more resilient sled using a 20&#39; tow strap&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m really happy with this setup. The cardboard works well on my reasonably smooth basement floor. It will eventually wear, but with the amount of online shopping my family does we&amp;rsquo;re never lacking fresh cardboard. Though, if the dragging surface were rougher, I&amp;rsquo;d imagine I&amp;rsquo;d have to use a different solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding useful pieces of equipment to a home gym doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be expensive or complicated. And, simple additions like this keep workouts engaging and fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benefits of sled training with a tow strap are numerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simple.&lt;/strong&gt; Really hard to mess up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cheap.&lt;/strong&gt; Just time, a stack of weights, and a ten dollar tow strap is all the investment you need to get started.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Safe.&lt;/strong&gt; You can do these by yourself. If you fail, there&amp;rsquo;s nothing that can fall and crush you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Versatile.&lt;/strong&gt; You can do these heavy for strength. You can do these lighter for cardio. You can drag it forward or backward. Or, you can pull it arm-over-arm. Using just a tow strap you have enough equipment for a full body workout.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things you can do with this include &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/MW5HfC5V_YI&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Arm-Over-Arm Pulls&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KKEceC_t2bY&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Reverse Sled Drag&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I Prioritize Strength Training</title>
      <link>http://quakkels.com/posts/why-i-prioritize-strength-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://quakkels.com/posts/why-i-prioritize-strength-training/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the last few years, I&amp;rsquo;ve taken up a new hobby; strength training. It&amp;rsquo;s something I&amp;rsquo;ve really grown to love. Though, sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s hard to articulate exactly why strength training has taken such a permanent position in my weekly routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was a sedentary person my quality of life decreased every year. Even when I was in my mid 20s I was not &amp;ldquo;strong&amp;rdquo; and frequent back and shoulder pain would frustrate me for weeks at a time. Every year my bodyweight would creep up, my strength would diminish, and I&amp;rsquo;d be a little less capable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t own anything in your life. You don&amp;rsquo;t own your fitness. You don&amp;rsquo;t own your health&amp;hellip; You&amp;rsquo;re always constantly needing to work at it&amp;hellip; If you don&amp;rsquo;t, you lose it. So, you&amp;rsquo;re &amp;ldquo;paying the man.&amp;rdquo; ― &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=si_w5Jze-zg&amp;amp;t=330s&#34;&gt;Josh Bridges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was losing my physical liberty. I was getting slower, weaker, and less resilient to everyday life. I&amp;rsquo;d spend my time being anxious about whether my back pain would get unbearable if I sat in the wrong chair for too long. I&amp;rsquo;d wake up in the morning in pain because I slept on my shoulder the wrong way. Utterly miserable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is why strength training is important. It &amp;ldquo;pays the man&amp;rdquo; so I can keep my physical liberty. It makes me more useful to my family and my community. It sets an example for my offspring that it important to be active and work hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strong people are harder to kill than weak people and more useful in general.
― &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/432892-strong-people-are-harder-to-kill-than-weak-people-and&#34;&gt;Mark Rippetoe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Muscular strength is inversely and independently associated with death from all causes and cancer in men, even after adjusting for cardiorespiratory fitness and other potential confounders. ― &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2453303/&#34;&gt;Association between muscular strength and mortality in men: prospective cohort study&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#39;http://quakkels.com/images/first400plusdeadlift.png&#39; style=&#34;float:right;padding:5px&#34;&gt;Strength training is an exercise in success. A person who follows a strength program and is disciplined will see improvements in their strength. They will be able to lift more, move more, and do more. That success reinforces confidence in one&amp;rsquo;s ability.  The first time I deadlifted over 400 pounds was hard hard work paying off, and it felt great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I have not seen anyone come up with a better list for &amp;ldquo;why train&amp;rdquo; than Jim Wendler:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For physical and mental health.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For self-improvement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To challenge yourself physically and mentally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To develop the bite that may help you through difficult times.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To honor all the men who have fought before you; it is part of your DNA to fight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To show/prove to yourself that you can change through will.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In a world of &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo;, it keeps your teeth sharp.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because we don&amp;rsquo;t have to chop wood anymore.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being stronger is ALWAYS better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To understand that there is cause and effect to action; and inaction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A stronger body can equal a stronger mind can equal a stronger body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is zero negative consequence to being a stronger man.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To be a great example to your children; fat, weak and ignorant is not a good role model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To exhaust your body and mind so as to put up with weak fools and ignorant beggars who demand what you have earned.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To learn self-reliance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To understand that compassion and empathy is noble but not given lightly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because a mentally and physically dangerous man will always be needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;― &lt;a href=&#34;https://jimwendler.com/blogs/jimwendler-com/what-is-the-reason-for-me-to-do-this&#34;&gt;Jim Wendler&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s why I train strength.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>