<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Fitness on Quakkels.com</title>
    <link>https://quakkels.com/tags/fitness/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Fitness on Quakkels.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://quakkels.com/tags/fitness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Building Strength of Character</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/developing-strength-of-character/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/developing-strength-of-character/</guid>
      <description>I wrote the first draft of this article all the way back in February of 2019. This started as a quick guide for how to build good habits using principles from physical training. But it quickly grew when I wanted to explore how to identify good character and good virtue. Back then I didn&amp;rsquo;t realize how big this topic is and how many different ways of answering it there are. So, I continued exploring the topic, and enjoying the underlying philosophy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Program Review: Mike Westerling&#39;s Basic Strongman</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/westerling-basic-strongman-program-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/westerling-basic-strongman-program-review/</guid>
      <description>This is my review of Basic Strongman. Basic Strongman is a program by Mike Westerling that I spent the last 12 weeks running. It&amp;rsquo;s a 3-day-a-week program for general strength and the sport of Strongman.
My Lifting History First a little about me to give you some context for this review. I&amp;rsquo;m 35 and not particularly athletic. Four years ago I started taking strength training seriously. I had gone to commercial gyms off and on for a couple years before building a home gym.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Home Gym Outfitting; Train with a Sled</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/home_gym_outfitting_train_with_a_sled/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/home_gym_outfitting_train_with_a_sled/</guid>
      <description>Outfitting a home gym with a sled for drags and arm-over-arm pulls is simple. You don&amp;rsquo;t need to spend hundreds of dollars on equipment or gym memberships in order to train with a sled. You also don&amp;rsquo;t really need any tools or handyman skills to get started.
When I first wanted to add arm-over-arm pulls to work my cardio, grip, arms, and back, I looked around and found a few different options.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I Prioritize Strength Training</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/why-i-prioritize-strength-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/why-i-prioritize-strength-training/</guid>
      <description>Over the last few years, I&amp;rsquo;ve taken up a new hobby; strength training. It&amp;rsquo;s something I&amp;rsquo;ve really grown to love. Though, sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s hard to articulate exactly why strength training has taken such a permanent position in my weekly routine.
When I was a sedentary person my quality of life decreased every year. Even when I was in my mid 20s I was not &amp;ldquo;strong&amp;rdquo; and frequent back and shoulder pain would frustrate me for weeks at a time.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>