<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Virtues on Quakkels.com</title>
    <link>https://quakkels.com/tags/virtues/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Virtues on Quakkels.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://quakkels.com/tags/virtues/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Meno and Authority Over Virtue</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202310_1_meno_and_authority_over_virtue/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202310_1_meno_and_authority_over_virtue/</guid>
      <description>Online Great Books recently hosted a live discussion session on Plato&amp;rsquo;s Meno. That encouraged me to pick it up again. It&amp;rsquo;s such a fun read.
So, as Meno asked, can virtue be taught?
Before answering the question, Socrates tells Meno that he needs an explanation of what virtue means. Meno lists a few virtues, but Socrates objects to any answer that uses a list of virtues to explain what virtue is.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Create the Culture</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202307_2_create_the_culture/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202307_2_create_the_culture/</guid>
      <description>Lackluster and lame excuses for entertainment have been piling up over the last few years, and Hollywood has lost its shine. What&amp;rsquo;s left is a grating subversion of my culture. It&amp;rsquo;s to the point that I tend to ignore new releases unless they&amp;rsquo;re recommended by people I trust. When big studios announce that they&amp;rsquo;ve acquired a beloved IP, or are remaking a classic story, there&amp;rsquo;s no excitement left. There&amp;rsquo;s no anticipation other than dread for whatever flop they&amp;rsquo;ll end up delivering.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Pilgrim&#39;s Hope</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202305_3_the_pilgrims_hope/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202305_3_the_pilgrims_hope/</guid>
      <description>John Bunyan&amp;rsquo;s classic, The Pilgrim&amp;rsquo;s Progress, is a book that deserves a permanent place on your bookshelf. It&amp;rsquo;s right up there with The Hobbit, and The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe. Every time I read it, I&amp;rsquo;m struck by a new part of the story. The re-readability factor is high.
The last time I read The Pilgrim&amp;rsquo;s Progress, I was inspired by Christian&amp;rsquo;s courage in the face of evil. This time, I am struck by how Christian&amp;rsquo;s hope kept him from succumbing to despair.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Does Superversive Mean?</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202305_1_whatdoessuperversivemean/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202305_1_whatdoessuperversivemean/</guid>
      <description>According to the science fiction author John C. Wright, the term &amp;ldquo;superversive&amp;rdquo; was first coined by Tom Simon. The first mention of superversive that I could find on Simon&amp;rsquo;s blog was from all the way back in 2003. Then, in 2014, the word was used in the title of The Superversive Literary Movement.
Tom Simon, and others in the movement, recognized that fiction and storytelling has been increasingly used as propaganda to undermine virtue and traditional values.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Fairy Tale Horror, Little Red Riding Hood</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202304_3_fairy_tale_horror_little_red_riding_hood/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202304_3_fairy_tale_horror_little_red_riding_hood/</guid>
      <description>When I decided to analyze Little Red Riding Hood, I was not expecting to find a story that bludgeoned the reader (or listener) over the head with a spiked bat. But that&amp;rsquo;s exactly what this version of the story does. It&amp;rsquo;s a full fledged horror story that has a moral for the kids, but there&amp;rsquo;s also a moral for the adults reading it.
The version of Little Red Riding Hood featured in the Junior Classics Fairy and Wonder Tales (published in 1918) was originally written down by Charles Perrault in the seventeenth century, though people point out that he&amp;rsquo;s probably not the source of the original idea.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Fairy Tale of Hansel and Grethel</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202304_2_the_fairy_tale_of_hansel_and_grethel/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202304_2_the_fairy_tale_of_hansel_and_grethel/</guid>
      <description>Hansel and Grethel is the story about two siblings who survive being abandoned by their guardians, they escape capture by a witch, and they reunite with their father as a happy family in the end. There are many different versions of the story, but I&amp;rsquo;m going to focus on the story by The Brothers Grimm.
I got my hands on a version that was published in 1918 in an anthology series called Junior Classics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Pilgrim&#39;s Courage</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202108_the_pilgrims_courage/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202108_the_pilgrims_courage/</guid>
      <description>I don&amp;rsquo;t remember how old I was when I first read an abridged version of John Bunyan&amp;rsquo;s Christian allegory, The Pilgrim&amp;rsquo;s Progress. It&amp;rsquo;s a great book, and the abridged version (which I&amp;rsquo;ve unfortunately misplaced at some point) had great illustrations and was very approachable when I was a boy.
John Bunyan lived in England during the 17th century. He witnessed civil war, plague, and he experienced religious persecution. He wrote the first part of The Pilgrim&amp;rsquo;s Progress while in prison for not following the Church of England.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building Strength of Character</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/developing-strength-of-character/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/developing-strength-of-character/</guid>
      <description>I wrote the first draft of this article all the way back in February of 2019. This started as a quick guide for how to build good habits using principles from physical training. But it quickly grew when I wanted to explore how to identify good character and good virtue. Back then I didn&amp;rsquo;t realize how big this topic is and how many different ways of answering it there are. So, I continued exploring the topic, and enjoying the underlying philosophy.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
