<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Virtues on Quakkels.com</title>
    <link>https://quakkels.com/tags/virtues/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Virtues on Quakkels.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://quakkels.com/tags/virtues/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Fairy Tale of Hansel and Grethel</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202304_2_the_fairy_tale_of_hansel_and_grethel/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202304_2_the_fairy_tale_of_hansel_and_grethel/</guid>
      <description>Hansel and Grethel is the story about two siblings who survive being abandoned by their guardians, they escape capture by a witch, and they reunite with their father as a happy family in the end. There are many different versions of the story, but I&amp;rsquo;m going to focus on the story by The Brothers Grimm.
I got my hands on a version that was published in 1918 in an anthology series called Junior Classics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Pilgrim&#39;s Courage</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202108_the_pilgrims_courage/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202108_the_pilgrims_courage/</guid>
      <description>I don&amp;rsquo;t remember how old I was when I first read an abridged version of John Bunyan&amp;rsquo;s Christian allegory, The Pilgrim&amp;rsquo;s Progress. It&amp;rsquo;s a great book, and the abridged version (which I&amp;rsquo;ve unfortunately misplaced at some point) had great illustrations and was very approachable when I was a boy.
John Bunyan lived in England during the 17th century. He witnessed civil war, plague, and he experienced religious persecution. He wrote the first part of The Pilgrim&amp;rsquo;s Progress while in prison for not following the Church of England.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building Strength of Character</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/developing-strength-of-character/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/developing-strength-of-character/</guid>
      <description>I wrote the first draft of this article all the way back in February of 2019. This started as a quick guide for how to build good habits using principles from physical training. But it quickly grew when I wanted to explore how to identify good character and good virtue. Back then I didn&amp;rsquo;t realize how big this topic is and how many different ways of answering it there are. So, I continued exploring the topic, and enjoying the underlying philosophy.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
