<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Philosophy on Quakkels.com</title>
    <link>https://quakkels.com/tags/philosophy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Philosophy on Quakkels.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://quakkels.com/tags/philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Fairy Tale of Hansel and Grethel</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202304_2_the_fairy_tale_of_hansel_and_grethel/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202304_2_the_fairy_tale_of_hansel_and_grethel/</guid>
      <description>Hansel and Grethel is the story about two siblings who survive being abandoned by their guardians, they escape capture by a witch, and they reunite with their father as a happy family in the end. There are many different versions of the story, but I&amp;rsquo;m going to focus on the story by The Brothers Grimm.
I got my hands on a version that was published in 1918 in an anthology series called Junior Classics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two Foundational Principles for Dialogue</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202304_essentials_for_healthy_conversation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202304_essentials_for_healthy_conversation/</guid>
      <description>There are two non-negotiable beliefs that are essential to healthy dialogue.
 There is such a thing as truth. The truth is available to every reasonable person.  A healthy dialogue happens when opposing viewpoints articulate and evaluate arguments in a search for the truth.
Participants in dialogue must agree that truth exists. If there isn&amp;rsquo;t agreement that truth exists, then they are engaged in a futile exercise. It&amp;rsquo;s literally pointless.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building Strength of Character</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/developing-strength-of-character/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/developing-strength-of-character/</guid>
      <description>I wrote the first draft of this article all the way back in February of 2019. This started as a quick guide for how to build good habits using principles from physical training. But it quickly grew when I wanted to explore how to identify good character and good virtue. Back then I didn&amp;rsquo;t realize how big this topic is and how many different ways of answering it there are. So, I continued exploring the topic, and enjoying the underlying philosophy.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
