<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Edification on Quakkels.com</title>
    <link>http://quakkels.com/tags/edification/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Edification on Quakkels.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://quakkels.com/tags/edification/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Developing Strength of Character</title>
      <link>http://quakkels.com/posts/developing-strength-of-character/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://quakkels.com/posts/developing-strength-of-character/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Lately I&amp;rsquo;ve been really interested in ways of programming life. And, when I say &amp;lsquo;programming&amp;rsquo; I don&amp;rsquo;t mean it in the digital sense. Rather, I mean it in the sense of forming a constructive routine that facilitates positive change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years I&amp;rsquo;ve seen how adopting strenuous routines can change my life. Habitual strenuous physical training and diet routines can make large positive changes in a methodical and progressive manner. Looking back on my journey to this point I am able to appreciate how very difficult and large changes can be accomplished incrementally with purposeful actions. And my life is happier for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach can be observed in other areas of life as well. The most obvious is education. To become educated, the student follows a &amp;lsquo;program&amp;rsquo; in the form of a curriculum. He studies each day until the program is completed. If the student reads the material and does the exercises then at the end he will have new knowledge available to apply in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physical ability and mental ability are two areas where it&amp;rsquo;s reasonably easy to measure progress by testing. I can go to the gym and test how much weight I&amp;rsquo;m able to lift or how far I can run in a given time frame. Likewise for my education level. I can test my knowledge against the rules or facts that the program presents. But, what if you wanted to measure incremental progress for something more nebulous such as strength of character. That gets much more difficult to track. Without tracking progress it&amp;rsquo;s easy to abandon the path to the goal before a habit is formed. No one &lt;em&gt;wants&lt;/em&gt; to do strenuous activity without seeing results. Seeing results over time means that we need data to track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To develop strength of character the desired virtues need to be identified. Once the virtues are identified then we need to measure how well they&amp;rsquo;re adhered to. Benjamin Franklin&amp;rsquo;s technique for developing his character was to identify &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thirteenvirtues.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;thirteen virtues&lt;/a&gt;. Every day he would evaluate how well he embodied those virtues which helped him track his progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fake-it-til-you-make-it&#34;&gt;Fake It &amp;lsquo;til You Make It&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strength of character is realized by being virtuous. The oft repeated adage &amp;ldquo;Fake it until you make it&amp;rdquo; is actually an ancient principle from Aristotle. He asserted that we get virtues by first &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://www.interlog.com/~girbe/ethics2.html&#34;&gt;practicing or exercising them&lt;/a&gt;. This really helps us understand what virtues are. Sharpness is a virtue of a knife. I knife is virtuous when it is sharp. In the same way people are patient when they are practicing patience, and they are temperate when they are practicing self-control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;identify-your-virtues&#34;&gt;Identify your Virtues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Identifying the virtues you want must be step one. Essentially this is goal setting. You could start with the Seven Heavenly Virtues, Ben Franklin&amp;rsquo;s 13 Virtues, or you could come up with your own. Whatever virtues you choose, I think it&amp;rsquo;s important to give them definitions that are clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal virtues are shaped by my faith, my biology, and my family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;developing-the-program&#34;&gt;Developing the Program&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program is all about the path to making virtues second nature. When I train for physical strength, I have a program I plan and follow to incrementally make progress towards becoming stronger. This is something I&amp;rsquo;m able to practice on a daily basis and see progress and develop a habit of being physically strong. In the same way there needs to be a plan for developing virtues to increase strength of character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laziness leads to depression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initiative leads to growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuously doing things that progressively get harder leads to satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qKhgILOgmug&#34;&gt;Barbell Logic: Refining Power of Voluntary Hardship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thirteenvirtues.com/&#34;&gt;Thirteenvirtues.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/a-happy-life-may-not-be-a-meaningful-life/&#34;&gt;A Happy Life May Not Be a Meaningful Life&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pursuit-of-happiness.org/history-of-happiness/aristotle/&#34;&gt;The Pursuit of Happiness, Introduction: Aristotle&amp;rsquo;s Definition of Happiness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>