<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Quakkels.com</title>
    <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Quakkels.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://quakkels.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Simple Fix for Savage Axis Failure to Feed</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202306_1_simple_fix_for_savage_axis_failure_to_feed/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202306_1_simple_fix_for_savage_axis_failure_to_feed/</guid>
      <description>I bought my first deer rifle in 2021. Friends recommended I try Savage, and I found one. It was a Savage Axis in 30-06 for right around $350 bucks at Cabela&amp;rsquo;s. I felt so lucky because, if you remember, guns were in high demand in 2021. Unfortunately, that lucky feeling was shortly followed by astonishment when I saw all the .308 on the shelves, with nary a box of 30-06 anywhere.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Pilgrim&#39;s Hope</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202305_3_the_pilgrims_hope/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202305_3_the_pilgrims_hope/</guid>
      <description>John Bunyan&amp;rsquo;s classic, The Pilgrim&amp;rsquo;s Progress, is a book that deserves a permanent place on your bookshelf. It&amp;rsquo;s right up there with The Hobbit, and The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe. Every time I read it, I&amp;rsquo;m struck by a new part of the story. The re-readability factor is high.
The last time I read The Pilgrim&amp;rsquo;s Progress, I was inspired by Christian&amp;rsquo;s courage in the face of evil. This time, I am struck by how Christian&amp;rsquo;s hope kept him from succumbing to despair.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How To Use RSS</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202305_2_how_to_use_rss/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202305_2_how_to_use_rss/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes my readers tell me that my RSS feed is broken. They click on the &amp;ldquo;RSS Feed&amp;rdquo; link expecting to be subscribed to my blog. But, instead they just see a bunch of computery gibberish filling their screen.
RSS, for all its benefits, isn&amp;rsquo;t as intuitive as a Facebook timeline or Twitter feed. But, with a little explanation, I think anyone can use RSS to build information feeds that are exactly what they want.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Does Superversive Mean?</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202305_1_whatdoessuperversivemean/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202305_1_whatdoessuperversivemean/</guid>
      <description>According to the science fiction author John C. Wright, the term &amp;ldquo;superversive&amp;rdquo; was first coined by Tom Simon. The first mention of superversive that I could find on Simon&amp;rsquo;s blog was from all the way back in 2003. Then, in 2014, the word was used in the title of The Superversive Literary Movement.
Tom Simon, and others in the movement, recognized that fiction and storytelling has been increasingly used as propaganda to undermine virtue and traditional values.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Fairy Tale Horror, Little Red Riding Hood</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202304_3_fairy_tale_horror_little_red_riding_hood/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202304_3_fairy_tale_horror_little_red_riding_hood/</guid>
      <description>When I decided to analyze Little Red Riding Hood, I was not expecting to find a story that bludgeoned the reader (or listener) over the head with a spiked bat. But that&amp;rsquo;s exactly what this version of the story does. It&amp;rsquo;s a full fledged horror story that has a moral for the kids, but there&amp;rsquo;s also a moral for the adults reading it.
The version of Little Red Riding Hood featured in the Junior Classics Fairy and Wonder Tales (published in 1918) was originally written down by Charles Perrault in the seventeenth century, though people point out that he&amp;rsquo;s probably not the source of the original idea.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Fairy Tale of Hansel and Grethel</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202304_2_the_fairy_tale_of_hansel_and_grethel/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202304_2_the_fairy_tale_of_hansel_and_grethel/</guid>
      <description>Hansel and Grethel is the story about two siblings who survive being abandoned by their guardians, they escape capture by a witch, and they reunite with their father as a happy family in the end. There are many different versions of the story, but I&amp;rsquo;m going to focus on the story by The Brothers Grimm.
I got my hands on a version that was published in 1918 in an anthology series called Junior Classics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two Foundational Principles for Dialogue</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202304_essentials_for_healthy_conversation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202304_essentials_for_healthy_conversation/</guid>
      <description>There are two non-negotiable beliefs that are essential to healthy dialogue.
 There is such a thing as truth. The truth is available to every reasonable person.  A healthy dialogue happens when opposing viewpoints articulate and evaluate arguments in a search for the truth.
Participants in dialogue must agree that truth exists. If there isn&amp;rsquo;t agreement that truth exists, then they are engaged in a futile exercise. It&amp;rsquo;s literally pointless.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Pilgrim&#39;s Courage</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202108_the_pilgrims_courage/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202108_the_pilgrims_courage/</guid>
      <description>I don&amp;rsquo;t remember how old I was when I first read an abridged version of John Bunyan&amp;rsquo;s Christian allegory, The Pilgrim&amp;rsquo;s Progress. It&amp;rsquo;s a great book, and the abridged version (which I&amp;rsquo;ve unfortunately misplaced at some point) had great illustrations and was very approachable when I was a boy.
John Bunyan lived in England during the 17th century. He witnessed civil war, plague, and he experienced religious persecution. He wrote the first part of The Pilgrim&amp;rsquo;s Progress while in prison for not following the Church of England.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Develop an ASP.NET Core Site on Linux</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202108_develop_an_aspnetcore_site_on_linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202108_develop_an_aspnetcore_site_on_linux/</guid>
      <description>There&amp;rsquo;s no doubt about it, C# is my favorite language. It breaks my heart whenever anyone points out that it&amp;rsquo;s basically just Java. (Looking at you, Robert C. Martin.) Though it may be inspired and even derived from Java, I much prefer the C# and .NET ecosystem. I&amp;rsquo;m sure familiarity plays a large part in my preference for it, as well as some old-fashioned nostalgia, and perhaps even a simple convenience factor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Framework is an Implementation Detail</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202107_a_framework_is_an_implementation_detail/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202107_a_framework_is_an_implementation_detail/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve previously written about my opinion of how programmers should consider frameworks. I was delighted to hear Robert C Martin express a similar point of view in a Q&amp;amp;A session after his Clean Architecture and Design talk at ITkonekt 2019.
 Frameworks are wonderful things. You can get a lot done with a framework. You get a framework like Spring or Rails, or JSF, or JPA. Any of those neat little frameworks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hand Tool Woodworking</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/hand-tool-woodworking/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/hand-tool-woodworking/</guid>
      <description>I recently took up hand tool woodworking. I&amp;rsquo;m not good at it. But I&amp;rsquo;m having fun.
These are my favorite resources for learning about it.
 The English Woodworker Rex Krueger Wood By Wright  A Bench As is the case with many beginners; my first woodworking project was my bench. I decided to build a Low Roman Workbench after seeing what Rex Krueger and Christopher Schwarz had to say about them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RSS is Wonderful</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/rss-is-wonderful/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/rss-is-wonderful/</guid>
      <description>I am not a big social media guy anymore. Over the last few years I&amp;rsquo;ve been actively avoiding it. I&amp;rsquo;m not a fan of each platform&amp;rsquo;s privacy concerns, and users need to be very cautious to avoid flamewars and infinite doomscrolling. If we aren&amp;rsquo;t careful, social media&amp;rsquo;s default state seems to devolve into just destroying trust and goodwill. I prefer society in real life.
However, avoiding social media means that we lose a lot of interesting articles, funny memes, and informative videos that are shared on those platforms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Favorite Tools on Linux</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/my-favorite-tools-on-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/my-favorite-tools-on-linux/</guid>
      <description>Last year I decided to take on the challenge of running just Linux. I wanted to see how good (or bad) the experience would be, and whether it&amp;rsquo;d be painful enough that I&amp;rsquo;d go back to using Windows. I went ahead and installed Linux Mint on my primary personal laptop. I did not dual boot Windows. This meant I stopped using Windows 10 unless it was work related. Thankfully, I don&amp;rsquo;t really miss Windows 10 that much.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building Strength of Character</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/developing-strength-of-character/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/developing-strength-of-character/</guid>
      <description>I wrote the first draft of this article all the way back in February of 2019. This started as a quick guide for how to build good habits using principles from physical training. But it quickly grew when I wanted to explore how to identify good character and good virtue. Back then I didn&amp;rsquo;t realize how big this topic is and how many different ways of answering it there are. So, I continued exploring the topic, and enjoying the underlying philosophy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Credit Card Processing with Python</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/credit-card-processing-with-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/credit-card-processing-with-python/</guid>
      <description>If you run a business, charity, or any organization that accepts money, a professional online payment feature on your website is a great way for your patrons to conveniently pay you.
Here&amp;rsquo;s how such a payment feature can be implemented in Python with Authorize.net.
Create a Sandbox Account If you&amp;rsquo;re a programmer interested in building a project yourself, then you&amp;rsquo;ll need to visit Authorize.net and create a sandbox account. Your sandbox account will let you test your payment processing integration without actually charging credit cards, and without needing to set up a Merchant Account with your bank.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building Blocks of Function Components in React</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/building-blocks-of-function-components-in-react/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/building-blocks-of-function-components-in-react/</guid>
      <description>Class based components aren&amp;rsquo;t the only way to build rich user interfaces in React. Here are some building blocks that can be used to build the same dynamic experiences using Function Components.
Key JavaScript Concepts JavaScript Arrow Functions Since React apps use a build system to generate the runtime code, we&amp;rsquo;re able to take advantage of ES6 syntax via transpilers without needing to worry about browser support. This gives us access to Arrow Functions syntax which are lambda functions in JavaScript.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Program Review: Mike Westerling&#39;s Basic Strongman</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/westerling-basic-strongman-program-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/westerling-basic-strongman-program-review/</guid>
      <description>This is my review of Basic Strongman. Basic Strongman is a program by Mike Westerling that I spent the last 12 weeks running. It&amp;rsquo;s a 3-day-a-week program for general strength and the sport of Strongman.
My Lifting History First a little about me to give you some context for this review. I&amp;rsquo;m 35 and not particularly athletic. Four years ago I started taking strength training seriously. I had gone to commercial gyms off and on for a couple years before building a home gym.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GitHub Pages and Quakkels.com</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/quakkels-dot-com-now-with-https/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/quakkels-dot-com-now-with-https/</guid>
      <description>So I must&amp;rsquo;ve been under a rock for the last 21 months because it wasn&amp;rsquo;t until this week that I learned that GitHub Pages now supports SSL certificates for custom domains. They&amp;rsquo;ve had SSL support since 2016 for sites using {user}.github.io domains. But it has also been available for custom domain sites (like this one) since May of 2018.
Before the feature was upgraded there were hacks to get around the custom domain limitation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flat is Better Than Nested Versus Single Entry Single Exit</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/single-entry-single-exit/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2019 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/single-entry-single-exit/</guid>
      <description>As a program ages and receives updates, more and more features are built. Logic is added and the code becomes increasingly more complicated to read and understand. So programmers invent recommended practices to manage the complexity and to preserve the maintainability of their code. The goal being to keep the cognitive load to minimum levels so the programmer can work efficiently.
One popular practice is to avoid nested code when possible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functions for Documentation Instead of Comments</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/functions-for-documentation-instead-of-comments/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2019 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/functions-for-documentation-instead-of-comments/</guid>
      <description>Using good function naming and composition will decrease the need for gratuitous comments and increase your code’s readability.
I&amp;rsquo;ve become convinced that comments are often worth avoiding. Comments aren&amp;rsquo;t subject to a compiler nor to an interpreter. Code may change and the corresponding comment often remains as it was. Except now the comment is misleading. This makes maintaining the code unnecessarily difficult.
Use Function Names to Document Code Consider this code that determines the &amp;ldquo;Day of the Programmer&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Naming Things Clearly</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/clean-names/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2019 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/clean-names/</guid>
      <description>Clean Code by Robert C. Martin is one of my favorite programming texts. It has a chapter called Meaningful Names wherein principles for the clear and clean naming of code elements are explained.
When we write code we should be considering the programmer who follows us. Sometimes it may be ourselves who have not touched the code for months or years. The programmer working in previously written code will need to study it to try and recognize the intention and systems of the original author.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Run Plex on an Ubuntu Server at Home</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/run-plex-on-ubuntu-server-at-home/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/run-plex-on-ubuntu-server-at-home/</guid>
      <description>Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve decided that having limited high quality entertainment choices is better than having endless choices that are of questionable quality. So my household decided to end our Netflix subscription. This decision motivated me to build a private streaming media server for our home. Here is how I created a home media server with Plex and a home server tower.
Choosing the Media Server There are two popular software options for home media server.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started with Mobile Development and Xamarin</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/getting-started-with-mobile-development-and-xamarin/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/getting-started-with-mobile-development-and-xamarin/</guid>
      <description>Xamarin enables programmers to write native mobile applications for both Android and iOS using C# and free development tools like Visual Studio Community Edition. This means that if you&amp;rsquo;re invested in the .NET ecosystem and the C# language, you can write cross-platform mobile applications using technology that&amp;rsquo;s already familiar to you.
 A note on development for iOS: You will need a mac in order to build iOS versions of the app.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Home Gym Outfitting; Train with a Sled</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/home_gym_outfitting_train_with_a_sled/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/home_gym_outfitting_train_with_a_sled/</guid>
      <description>Outfitting a home gym with a sled for drags and arm-over-arm pulls is simple. You don&amp;rsquo;t need to spend hundreds of dollars on equipment or gym memberships in order to train with a sled. You also don&amp;rsquo;t really need any tools or handyman skills to get started.
When I first wanted to add arm-over-arm pulls to work my cardio, grip, arms, and back, I looked around and found a few different options.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started with Django</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/getting-started-python-django-vs-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/getting-started-python-django-vs-code/</guid>
      <description>Django is a Python framework that I&amp;rsquo;ve written about before. I&amp;rsquo;ve compared Django to ASP.NET MVC. But, I didn&amp;rsquo;t go into much detail about how to actually use Django to create a data driven website. That&amp;rsquo;s what I&amp;rsquo;ll cover now.
The goal for this &amp;lsquo;Getting Started&amp;rsquo; project is to get familiar with the basics of developing data driven web applications using Django, Models, Views, Templates, URLs, and Forms. By the end we&amp;rsquo;ll have a simple contact form that saves user submissions to the database, and displays that data to an administrator user.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Configuring Vim When Using Git Bash on Windows</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/configuring-vim-when-using-git-bash/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/configuring-vim-when-using-git-bash/</guid>
      <description>Occasionally I become enamored with the idea of becoming a Vim expert, or at least a competent Vim user. I work primarily in Windows environments so, though the desire exists, there aren&amp;rsquo;t many good opportunities to build Vim habits. There is a Vim on Windows release available. This has a GUI interface and an installer executable. Though if you have Git for Windows installed, then you already have Vim available. Git for Windows comes with the ever useful, Git Bash.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MySQL Quick Reference</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/mysql-quick-reference/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/mysql-quick-reference/</guid>
      <description>Shell Commands Set up security requirements: $ sudo mysql_secure_installation Open the MySQL CLI client and login using a password and the specified user: $ sudo mysql -u {user} -p MySQL Queries and Commands  Note that MySQL will not execute anything until it encounters a semicolon ; which indicates the end of a statement. This allows us to enter multi-line statements.
 Create User &amp;gt; CREATE USER &amp;#39;newuser&amp;#39;@&amp;#39;localhost&amp;#39; IDENTIFIED BY &amp;#39;password&amp;#39;; Give User Access to a Database &amp;gt; GRANT ALL PRIVILEGES ON * .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gogs on Raspberry PI</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/gogs-on-raspberry-pi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/gogs-on-raspberry-pi/</guid>
      <description>In a previous article I configured a headless Raspberry Pi for Wifi and SSH. Next, I&amp;rsquo;ll set up a personal Gogs server on it.
Change the Password First things first, change the password for the pi user to something different than raspberry.
$ passwd Changing password for pi. (current) UNIX password: Enter new UNIX password: Retype new UNIX password: passwd: password updated successfully Please tweet your new password to @quakkels /s</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I Prioritize Strength Training</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/why-i-prioritize-strength-training/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/why-i-prioritize-strength-training/</guid>
      <description>Over the last few years, I&amp;rsquo;ve taken up a new hobby; strength training. It&amp;rsquo;s something I&amp;rsquo;ve really grown to love. Though, sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s hard to articulate exactly why strength training has taken such a permanent position in my weekly routine.
When I was a sedentary person my quality of life decreased every year. Even when I was in my mid 20s I was not &amp;ldquo;strong&amp;rdquo; and frequent back and shoulder pain would frustrate me for weeks at a time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Configure Headless Raspberry Pi for Wifi and SSH</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/configure-headless-raspberry-pi-for-wifi-and-ssh/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/configure-headless-raspberry-pi-for-wifi-and-ssh/</guid>
      <description>Raspberry Pis are great little computers. Wonderful for running hobby services. But, whenever I start a new RPi project, I dislike needing to dig out my spare HDMI monitor and USB keyboard. I don&amp;rsquo;t like having to take up room and connect all that hardware to just enable SSH and Wifi which renders all that equipment unnecessary.
Recently I learned how to flash a new micro SD card and configure it to connect to my Wifi network and enable SSH before even turning on the RPi for the first time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identify Valid Standards</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/identify-valid-standards/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2017 07:26:36 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/identify-valid-standards/</guid>
      <description>I can&amp;rsquo;t tell you how many times I&amp;rsquo;ve been in software planning meetings when an engineer addressed the team and claimed that we should use {insert technology here} because it&amp;rsquo;s the &amp;ldquo;Industry Standard.&amp;rdquo; I also can&amp;rsquo;t tell you how many times I&amp;rsquo;ve done the same thing. I&amp;rsquo;ve gone into my boss&amp;rsquo;s office and claimed that we should use a particular stack or technology because it&amp;rsquo;s an &amp;ldquo;industry standard.&amp;rdquo;
This reasoning is attractive because on the surface it seems valid.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t Take Frameworks for Granted</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/dont-take-frameworks-for-granted/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2017 07:41:18 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/dont-take-frameworks-for-granted/</guid>
      <description>Frameworks can help jump-start productivity on projects. But be careful. Relying too much on frameworks could also limit yourself in the long run.
Whenever the opportunity presents itself, programmers should carefully consider whether using a framework is beneficial. It may provide immediate benefits, but there should be no magic happening that isn&amp;rsquo;t understood by the programmer.
Years ago, I learned how to make websites with C#. I had help from many books, tutorials, and co-workers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 Slack Tricks that Changed My Life</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/5-slack-tricks-that-changed-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/5-slack-tricks-that-changed-my-life/</guid>
      <description>Please excuse the &amp;ldquo;click-baity&amp;rdquo; title. Sometimes I like to exaggerate.
Slack plays a significant role in my daily communication. My team at work has been using Slack as our primary mode of textual communication for over a year. It is also used by developer communities in my local area. At first, it felt a little clumsy. No more clumsy than a typical chat program. But, channels started to accumulate. The number of Direct Message feeds grew.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Into the Nether: Linux</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/into-the-nether-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/into-the-nether-linux/</guid>
      <description>The first movie I saw that really got me excited about computers was WarGames. The WOPR was an inanimate object that just sat there on screen. But, it was still a complete character all by itself. It reacted to the Matthew Broderick character&amp;rsquo;s commands and questions and became something more clever than just a boring piece of hardware. The fictional software running inside the WOPR and Broderick&amp;rsquo;s character&amp;rsquo;s ability to interface with it created a story that was incredibly mystical and exciting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maintaining Your Vision</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/maintaining-your-vision/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/maintaining-your-vision/</guid>
      <description>Programmers are often creators. Being a creator takes vision. Vision to see the destination, and vision to see the course. The destination could be learning a new language or technology stack. The destination could be a product to be released to customers. It could be something done for personal edification. The course is determined by taking that larger goal and breaking it down to manageable steps.
The trick for successfully creating something, is to maintain that vision.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let&#39;s Scrape the Web with Python 3</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/lets-scrape-the-web-with-python-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/lets-scrape-the-web-with-python-3/</guid>
      <description>In the back of my mind I&amp;rsquo;ve always been intrigued by writing an application that can retrieve web pages over HTTP. It&amp;rsquo;s a fairly simple thing to do. We have a myriad of web browsers that do it for us. But there is just something about writing an application that operates independently of a browser and reaches out to touch the internet that I find fun and intriguing. So let&amp;rsquo;s do it&amp;hellip; in Python.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Happens When You Login?</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/what-happens-when-you-login/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/what-happens-when-you-login/</guid>
      <description>Your favorite website is asking you for your username and password.
Username? Password? Sure, you&amp;rsquo;ve got those. [You enter your username] then [you enter your password] then [you press enter] then boom, you&amp;rsquo;re logged into the website.
What actually just happened? Well, assuming that you entered correct login credentials, you can now access whatever members only area that site offers to those credentials. But before that, in the split seconds after you clicked login and before you saw your profile, the website had to verify that the credentials you entered were correct.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learn Insertion Sort with Video Game Discs</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/learn-insertion-sort-with-video-game-discs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/learn-insertion-sort-with-video-game-discs/</guid>
      <description>I think you could say I have an average number of video game discs. It&amp;rsquo;s not a huge number of games, but it is enough that it can be difficult to find a particular game if they&amp;rsquo;re not organized in a predictable way.
Enter insertion sort. Insertion sort is in the same family as the bubble sort in that its worst case complexity is O(n2). But in practice, it is usually a faster sort.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learn Bubble Sort with Playing Cards</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/learn-bubble-sort-with-playing-cards/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/learn-bubble-sort-with-playing-cards/</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;rsquo;s say you have an unordered list of numbers and you wanted to put them in order from lowest to highest value. How would you do that? You&amp;rsquo;re probably thinking that you would just look at all the numbers, find the lowest number and put it at the beginning of your list. Then you would find the next largest number and put it in the second spot in the list, and so on until you&amp;rsquo;ve ordered the entire list of numbers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let&#39;s talk to a SQLite database with Python</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/lets-talk-to-a-sqlite-database-with-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/lets-talk-to-a-sqlite-database-with-python/</guid>
      <description>As I write this, it&amp;rsquo;s the weekend. My wonderful wife brought home some amazing Jet Fuel XBold Dark Roast Coffee that is sure to keep me wired for the next several hours. Now what should I do? Let&amp;rsquo;s explore Python a little more by using it to talk to a database.
We&amp;rsquo;re a long way from my bread and butter. My goto technologies for database interaction are .NET, C# and Entity Framework CodeFirst with SQL Server 2005/2008.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ASP.NET MVC Compared to Django</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/asp-net-mvc-compared-to-dango/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/asp-net-mvc-compared-to-dango/</guid>
      <description>The MVC pattern is widely used in web development today. Regardless of whether you develop in C#, PHP, Python, Java, JavaScript, or Ruby, you won’t have any trouble finding a popular MVC pattern for your language of choice.
Being primarily a C# developer, I’ve been using ASP.NET MVC since version 1. It’s a great framework. It can be very good at getting a project off the ground quickly, especially when coupled with a good ORM such as NHibernate, or Entity Framework.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
