<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Computing on Quakkels.com</title>
    <link>https://quakkels.com/tags/computing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Computing on Quakkels.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://quakkels.com/tags/computing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How To Use RSS</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/202305_2_how_to_use_rss/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/202305_2_how_to_use_rss/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes my readers tell me that my RSS feed is broken. They click on the &amp;ldquo;RSS Feed&amp;rdquo; link expecting to be subscribed to my blog. But, instead they just see a bunch of computery gibberish filling their screen.
RSS, for all its benefits, isn&amp;rsquo;t as intuitive as a Facebook timeline or Twitter feed. But, with a little explanation, I think anyone can use RSS to build information feeds that are exactly what they want.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RSS is Wonderful</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/rss-is-wonderful/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/rss-is-wonderful/</guid>
      <description>I am not a big social media guy anymore. Over the last few years I&amp;rsquo;ve been actively avoiding it. I&amp;rsquo;m not a fan of each platform&amp;rsquo;s privacy concerns, and users need to be very cautious to avoid flamewars and infinite doomscrolling. If we aren&amp;rsquo;t careful, social media&amp;rsquo;s default state seems to devolve into just destroying trust and goodwill. I prefer society in real life.
However, avoiding social media means that we lose a lot of interesting articles, funny memes, and informative videos that are shared on those platforms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Favorite Tools on Linux</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/my-favorite-tools-on-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/my-favorite-tools-on-linux/</guid>
      <description>Last year I decided to take on the challenge of running just Linux. I wanted to see how good (or bad) the experience would be, and whether it&amp;rsquo;d be painful enough that I&amp;rsquo;d go back to using Windows. I went ahead and installed Linux Mint on my primary personal laptop. I did not dual boot Windows. This meant I stopped using Windows 10 unless it was work related. Thankfully, I don&amp;rsquo;t really miss Windows 10 that much.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Into the Nether: Linux</title>
      <link>https://quakkels.com/posts/into-the-nether-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quakkels.com/posts/into-the-nether-linux/</guid>
      <description>The first movie I saw that really got me excited about computers was WarGames. The WOPR was an inanimate object that just sat there on screen. But, it was still a complete character all by itself. It reacted to the Matthew Broderick character&amp;rsquo;s commands and questions and became something more clever than just a boring piece of hardware. The fictional software running inside the WOPR and Broderick&amp;rsquo;s character&amp;rsquo;s ability to interface with it created a story that was incredibly mystical and exciting.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
